<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons preached at Sherborne in Dorsetshire by William Lyford ... being his last sermons ...</title>
            <title>Sermons. Selections</title>
            <author>Lyford, William, 1598-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13672415</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13672415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 794:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons preached at Sherborne in Dorsetshire by William Lyford ... being his last sermons ...</title>
                  <title>Sermons. Selections</title>
                  <author>Lyford, William, 1598-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11, [1], 23.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall ... for Edward Forrest,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, II, 15-16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101164:1"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS PREACHED AT SHERBORNE <hi>IN DORSETSHIRE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM LYFORD <hi>B. D. Being his laſt</hi> SERMONS.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe words;</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, 16.</bibl> 
               <p>For, we are unto God a ſweet ſavour, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>ACADEMIA OXONIESIS</head>
               <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed by H. HALL Printer to the Univerſity, for EDVVARD FORREST. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:101164:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101164:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. COR. 2.15, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For we are unto God a ſweet ſavour, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo parts of Chap. 1. Shewing the cauſes of his Indulgence towards that excommunicate perſon, giving order for his reception into Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon his repentance teſtified. 2. The ſucceſſe of his Miniſtry, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>Now thanks be to God, &amp;c.</hi> The praiſe and glory of the ſucceſſe of our Miniſtrie is to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to God alone; he cauſeth us to triumph: q. d. not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding al the oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, we meet with all, yet God giveth us the conqueſt; where-ever we preach the Goſpel all Countries are brought into ſubjection to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the faith; he manifeſteth the ſavour q. d. the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpell is a ſweet perfume blowne about with the Breath of the Apoſtles preaching into all parts of the world, and doth ſweeten and ſeaſon them with ſaving knowledge. q. d. God never placeth the faithful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Goſpell in any place, but he uſeth to make it ſavorie and fruitfull unto ſome, in every place ſome were ſeaſoned with it. <hi>Ob.</hi> If ſo, why then doe ſo many in every place reject the Goſpell as an odious thing? You <hi>ſtinke in the noſtrills of ſome, and are counted as the filth of the world: Sol:</hi> True, unto ſome men we are ſo, but yet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, in his eſteeme and account of us, we are a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt; the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt ſpread
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101164:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>abroad by us is pleaſing to God, though not ſalvificall to all, q. d. we are a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, we are pleaſing, gratefull, and delightfull to God, becauſe, by us is ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad the ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, the knowledge of his ſweet mercy and grace to the corrupt world, to ſave filthy ſinners, that lay rotting and ſtinking in their ſinnes. <hi>v.</hi> 16. This ſweet doctrine is indifferently preacht to all, but it worketh in a very different manner; for as much as being received by beleevers, it produceth in them life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but being rejected by unbeleevers, it ſealeth up their condemnation, it is a killing word to them. Wee preach Chriſt a Saviour; for to know him, it is eternall life, but to them that diſobey him, a Judge. To ſome Chriſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched is the power of God, and the wiſdome of God. To others he is fooliſh neſſe, his Goſpell is unſavorie, a dead thing. To the one ſort he is a ſavour of life (i.) a vitall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, of ſpirituall life to life eternall, of ſpirituall death unto death eternall to the other. In the words. 3. 1. the nature of the Goſpell, a ſweet ſavour. 2. The eſteem that God hath of his Miniſterie, they are unto him a ſweet ſavour for their works ſake. 3. The power of the Goſpell, it is unto life or unto death; the one is <hi>effectus per ſe,</hi> that which comes from it in its own nature; the other <hi>per ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens</hi> that which follows upon the neglect &amp; contempt of 4. The difficultie of this calling, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent? he remoues from himſelfe the ſuſpicion of arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; for, neither he nor they are ſufficient Foure doctrines. Firſt, a ſound Miniſterie is a ſavorie Miniſterie, it ſends forth a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt to perfume the world: or The Goſpell Purely preached brings with it a ſweet ſmell &amp; ſavour to the ſoules of God's elect. Second doctrine. The faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt are well pleaſing, as a ſweet ſmelling ſavour unto God both in them that be ſaved &amp; in them that periſh. God eſteemes ſo of them, however the ſucceſſe be. Third doctrine. The ſame Miniſtery and the ſame doctrine preacht indifferently to all, hath not the ſame effects in all. It is to ſome a doctrine of life and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101164:3"/>ſalvation, it hath â ſpirituall ſavour and relliſh, but to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it is a deadly ſavour, it does the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no good. Fourth doctrine. Men are to be reckned in a ſtate of life or death, of periſhing or being ſaved, according as they doe, or doe not receive the ſavour, and relliſh the doctrine of our miniſterie of the Goſpell; (for, ſo the perſons are here diſtributed) I made choyce of this Text becauſe from hence ariſeth the fountaine of your everlaſting weale or woe, from peoples reſpect or diſreſpect to this ordinance. I thinke you are glad to ſee me now. But your aymes upon me ſhould be ſpirituall, for ſpirituall good. What the iſſue will be God knowes; if he hath more work for me, he will reſtore me to his houſe, and make you more diligent hearers, that ſo both may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce together: Firſt doctrine, A ſound Miniſtrie ſends forth a ſweet ſavour. The Breath of the Goſpell is a ſweet odour or ſmell; and God's faithfull Miniſters are they that carry it, &amp; blow it abroad to perfume &amp; ſeaſon the ſoules of ſinners, that ly ſtinking in their ſins and in a ſtate of condemnation Miniſters are (in regard of their neceſſitie and utilitie, or benefit to the world) compared to light, to ſhine to them that fit in darkneſſe; to ſalt, to ſeaſon and preſerve from putrifying; and in this place to a ſweet perfume, to make the men of earth to ſavour of Chriſt, of Religion, of Heaven. And that for two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt Reaſon. Becauſe they open the myſtery and riches of God's grace in Chriſt to loſt and undone man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> brought a Box of ointment of Spiknard, very pretious; <hi>And ſhe brake the Box, and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it on Chriſt's head, and the houſe was filled, Mark</hi> 14.3. <hi>Joh</hi> 12.3. Chriſt himſelfe is like that Box; the Miniſters open it, the Treaſures of wiſdome and mercy, that be in Chriſt, and poure it on your heads; &amp; the whole houſe where they preach is filled with the odour thereof; you carry the ſent of it upon you all the weeke after, yea as long as you live. Thus <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3. Chriſt is compared to rich oyntments: <hi>(becauſe of the ſavour of thy good oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.)</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101164:4"/>Chriſt was filled with all Graces, anointed with the holy Ghoſt and Power, &amp; the ſavour of theſe oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is ſmelt, when the Goſpell preached is perceived by ſenſe, or judgement, (for, by ſmell or ſavours is meant knowledge by ſenſe and feeling). It followes. <hi>Thy name is as ointment powred forth;</hi> Chriſt's name is by interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Anointed. By his name is meant the doctrine of his grace, the law of faith, and the preaching of that grace is called the <hi>Bearing of Chriſt's name before the Gentiles. Acts</hi> 9.15. That's the pouring forth of that ointment, <hi>Therefore doe the Virgins love thee,</hi> (that is) They that bee choſen of God and faithfull, who ſerve God with chaſt and pure mindes, and are not tainted with the common pollutions of the world. Theſe love Chriſt, they follow him, they are taken with the odour of his pretious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which they perceive ſenſible to revive and refreſh their ſoules. The ſecond reaſon is: Becauſe the breath of their doctrine doth blow upon dead ſoules, and doth breath into them the ſpirit of life. In <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.9. the Propher was willed to propheſie unto the winde, &amp; ſay, <hi>come O winde, and blowe upon theſe ſlaine, that they may live: ſo, I prophecied, and the breath came into them, and they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> The ſavour of Chriſt's doctrine is like this breath, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake ô North winde, and blow upon my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that the ſpice thereof may flow out:</hi> By this blowing is ſignified the miniſtration of his word and ſpirit beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on his people for their ſpirituall reviving and refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing. As on the contrary; The reſtraint of God's graces by wholſome doctrine, is ſignified by <hi>foure Angells hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the foure windes of the earth, that the winde ſhould not blowe on the earth nor on the ſea, Rev.</hi> 7.1. The ſavour of the knowledge of Chriſt is a breath of life; it is that by which corruption is purged away, which when it enters into the ſoule, it doth <hi>become a ſavour of life unto life;</hi> God maketh our words ſavorie and fruitfull to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: Againe, in this Metaphor of ſweet ſavour, is an allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the ointment, and the ſweet incenſe, which the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101164:4"/>Prieſts offered with their ſacrifices. So by the Goſpell we ſeaſon the ſoules of men, and bring them as a ſweet ſacrifice unto God. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.15.16. He ſpeaks of his miniſtration. <hi>That I ſhould be the Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt to the Gentiles, &amp;c.</hi> and the effect of it was, By it he had prepared a ſacrifice for God, the offering up of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. They were unto God an offering of a ſweet ſavour, acceptable to God, being ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt. A Sacrifice of the Goſpell muſt not be a dead thing, it muſt not be an uncleane or corrupt thing. But being breathed upon with this ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, <hi>We offer our ſelves to God a living ſacrifice, holy and acceptable by Jeſus Chriſt, Rom:</hi> 12.1. <hi>By preaching of faith we receive the ſpirit, Gal.</hi> 3.2. The third Reaſon. It ſends forth a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt to them that are already planted in Chriſt's garden, to comfort and refreſh their ſpirits. When our ſpirits be ſpent and weake, ſweet things burnt doe refreſh them. So <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Blow upon my garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow out.</hi> The miniſtration of the Goſpell cauſeth the ſweet-ſmelling fruits of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, faith, love, prayer, thankſgiving to flow out, that theſe fruits doe ripen, all graces are ſtrengthned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. Thus under God we are a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, (that is) we cauſe the ſweet ſavour to be ſent abroad, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we open Chriſt's riches to the world, becauſe by it, the dead ſoules are ſeaſoned, and they that live are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and refreſhed.</p>
            <p>Firſt Uſe. Are we a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt? Then ſee what a filthie thing ſin is, and what noyſome offenſive creatures men are, that have not beene perfumed with this heavenly knowledge. Second Uſe. Therefore never thinke thou haſt been a good hearer, or haſt profited by the Goſpell, till thy whole ſoule be filled and ſeaſoned with the ſavour of Jeſus Chriſt; where the Goſpell is purely preached &amp; received, <hi>ibi reperitur vis odoris Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> there the efficacy of Chriſt's ſavour is found: your rich perfumes of Leather or Cloath, they are laſting; the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101164:5"/>things perfumed will carry the ſent for a long time, yea it will never quite out: ſo if you be perfumed with the knowledge of Chriſt, It will make your affections, your delights, your comforts, your praiſes, your diſpraiſes, they will all ſavour of Chriſt; ſo will your tongue, ſo will your dealings, ſo will your outward man. They muſt all ſavour of Chriſt, elſe doe not thinke 'tis all well, elſe 'tis but like the perfuming of a dead carkaſſe, I obſerve you caſt your Roſemarie branches into the graves of your friends, the ſmell refreſheth you, but not the dead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is dead. And it is a ſigne, your ſoules are dead under a ſavorie miniſtrie, when they ſtill relliſh and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the earth, of rottenneſſe, of folly &amp; vanity: How few among us can ſay, the miniſtrie hath been the ſavour of Chriſt to me? Conſider your own thoughts &amp; waies, your wit, and diſcourſes, what doe they ſavour of? Of Chriſt? Of heavenly things? Nay rather of a Playbooke, of an Alehouſe, of Atheiſme, of Epicuriſme, of Worldly delights. Come to the Stateſmen and Polititians of this world, and what doe their counſells ſavour of. Of Chriſt? is the ſmell of Chriſt upon them? Nay rather of Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avell, of Turciſme, Come to the Gallants of our time, if Chriſt ſhould take them by their powdred hair, by their naked backs, by their painted and pictured faces. What doe they ſmell off? Of Chriſt? Of Grace? of Modeſty? Nay rather of Pride, wantonneſſe, diſcontent at God's workmanſhip, that has made them thus, not faire enough, not white enough? Conſider the waies of Chriſtians, their delights, their labours, their oppreſſions, their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant breaking. How little relliſh of Chriſt is to be found? Men may juſtly think, that ſuch have not lived under a Miniſterie, that ſavours of Chriſt. Surely all is not well with ſuch; Thou art not as yet one planted in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of ſpices; the ointment of Chriſt, which is the graces of the holy Ghoſt, have not yet deſcended upon thee; Chriſt ſpeakes thus to his Church; <hi>Cant</hi> 4.10. <hi>How much better is thy love then wine, and the ſmell of thy garments,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101164:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>then all ſpices.</hi> In <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.23. <hi>The Church admireth Chriſt's graces,</hi> and preferreth Chriſt's love before wine; here Chriſt doth the like of her love towards him: here Chriſt ſhewes how much hee is taken with the graces of his Church. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. The Church extolleth the ſavour of Chriſt's oyntments; here Chriſt doth hers. Which did ſend forth a ſweet ſavour, like ſweet-ſmelling ſpices. A Chriſtian is one anoynted with Chriſt's oyntment, and we muſt cary the ſent thereof upon all our actions: See <hi>Za.</hi> 14.20.21. It tells you how holineſſe ſhould abound in times of the Goſpell, <hi>In that day there ſhall be upon the Bells of the horſes, Holineſſe to the Lord, and the pots in the Lord's houſe ſhall be like the bowles before the Altar:</hi> uppon the plate, of gold, which the High Prieſt did weare on his forehead was engraven Holines to the Lord, Now that title muſt bee upon all things belonging to a Chriſtian, (for we are made Prieſts unto our God) as upon the Bridles of of our Horſes (that is) upon the inſtruments of war, of our labour, and of our Recreations. Holineſſe muſt bee upon our garments, upon our pots, (that is) upon the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our eating and drinking. Upon the Attire of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, may be written not Holineſſe to the Lord, but Pride, Lightneſſe, Vanitie, prodigalitie; upon their horſes &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, Rapine, Plunder, and violence; upon the Brims of their diſhes, Extortion, and oppreſſion; upon their Cups exceſſes, &amp;c. Whereas every thing belonging to a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſhould ſavour of Chriſtianitie. All the things and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſills and appurtenances of the Temple were counted and called holy in their kind, and in ſeverall degrees Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem was an holy city, <hi>and every pot in Jeruſalem ſhall be holy to the Lord.</hi> The houſe of the Lord was more then the city, and the pots thereof more holy. The Altar was more holy then the other parts of the, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Now the Holineſſe under the Goſpell ſhould thus riſe, the pots in Jeruſalem holy to the Lord: like the pots in the Lord's houſe: and the pots in the Lord's houſe like the Bowles before the Altar. The meaning ſeems to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101164:6"/>this; that the meaneſt things of common and ordinary uſe, whether in war or peace, ſhould now become holy &amp; be holily uſed, in the whole carriage &amp; converſation of a Chriſtian: whatſoever Chriſtians goe about to doe ſhould be as an acceptable ſacrifice to the Lord. 1 <hi>Pe.</hi> 2 5.</p>
            <p>The third uſe, how to Judge of a ſound Miniſtry of Chriſt; does it ſavour of Chriſt? of his doctrine? ſpirit? Counſells? of his righteouſneſſe? Graces? of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? does it tend to ſeaſon bad hearts? ſweeten corrupt tongues and lives? To make you relliſh of Chriſt? Tis one thing to ſavour of poets, of learning, of moralitie, another to ſavour of Chriſt, of regeneration. Chriſts perfume muſt be opened, that our faith may ſtand in his wiſdome, and in the power of God. It is a ſad thing to ſit under a dead, ſapleſſe, unſavorie Miniſtrie: But a ſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Miniſtrie is a choice mercy, a pretious bleſſing, and ſo to be reckoned of. One that ſavours of Chriſt himſelfe, and can ſpread that ſavour unto others: when ye can ſmell and taſte Chriſt in his doctrine, in his words, in his life, this is a choice mercie, becauſe it tends to the ſalvation of ſoules, and they ought to be unto us as a pretious perfume. Second doctrine. The faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt are pretious, as a ſweet ſmelling ſavour unto God; however the ſucceſſe of our Labours be, (unto God) we are a ſweet ſavour in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh. <hi>Paul</hi> doth dignifie in this ſpeech this ordinance of God, the better to worke in people an high eſteeme of it. However the world eſteemes of our office and perſons, yet unto God we are a ſweet ſavour. To teſtifie this Eſteeme of them, God is not aſhamed to call us his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Labourers together with God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Choſen veſſells to beare his name before the Gentiles:</hi> yea even where God is not pleaſed to worke with our Miniſtry, ſo far as to make it effectuall to the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of men, yet even there our Miniſtry is acceptable unto God. He joyeth and taketh pleaſure in it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101164:6"/>God teſtifieth his eſteeme of them, becauſe the injuries done to them, God takes as done to himſelfe. As by the law of nations injuries doneto an Embaſſadour are taken as done to the Prince that ſends him, he that receaveth a Prophet in my name, receaveth me; And he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and him that ſent me. And he giveth a ſpeciall charge concerning them, <hi>touch not mine anointed (next unto Kings) and doe my Prophets no harme.</hi> God will revenge the injuries done to them. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16. <hi>Rev</hi> 11.5. He that hurteth my witneſſes ſhall in like manner be killed. It is the laſt ſin that goeth before a generall judgment. But they mocked the meſſengers of God, till there was no remedy. It's a forerunner of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon an unthankfull people. Firſt uſe is to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us againſt all diſcouragements, the greateſt of which is want of ſucceſſe: what? though the world hate us, it hated Chriſt firſt: <hi>Paul</hi> firſt was made the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, even by his owne children, whom he had converted to the faith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14.15. he might expect better eſteeme from ſuch, yet he was hated by them. What? though manie periſh, and be the worſe for our preaching, yet our labour is acceptable, our doctrine ſound. God likes us when we preach damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the impenitent; It's a ſavorie doctrine, the breathing out of threatnings is the Advancing of Chriſt; The breathing out of threatnings is a ſavorie doctrine to them that believe it, it mortifies luſts, it kills nothing but ſin, it ſaves the ſoule; it's unſavorie to a man ſetled on his lees, but ſavory to believers. Second uſe if it be a ſweet ſavour to God, it ought alſo to be to us, if yee be ſonnes of God; O what a mercy the Goſpell is? It's a ſigne God hath a people there. The whole courſe of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mercy is comprehended in that one mercy. When <hi>Paul</hi> would ſumme up the advantages of the <hi>Jew</hi> above the <hi>Gentile,</hi> he doth it in this one word, <hi>(Chiefly)</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unto them were committed the Oracles of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. whereas the Gentiles were ſtrangers to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101164:7"/>of promiſes, and therefore without hope, and without: God in the world. How commeth it then about that they which are ſweet to God, are a ſtink in the no. ſtrills of the world It is a ſigne our ſenſes are much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered: when thoſe words, <hi>how beautifull are the feet of them which preach glad tidings,</hi> ſhall be turned, into, how ugly are the faces of them that bring this ſweet ſavour? That ſenſe alſo is much diſtempered. A deceitfull heart hath cauſed them to erre. Let me ſpeake unto England: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> your (Chiefly) your intereſt, your Crowne, your glory, lies in this, that thou enjoyeſt the breath of life. What advantage hath England above other Nations? Much every way: You that are Merchants and Travellers knowe it full well; we have enjoyed long peace, above foureſcore yeares (that was the longeſt reſt that Iſrael's land ever enjoyed, (<hi>Judges</hi> 3.30.) Under Kings and Queenes, which clothed us with skarlet, made ſilver as ſtones, and gold as the Sycomores, that filled our houſes with good things. The Riches of other nations were brought into us, yea their delights (as <hi>Solomons</hi> Apes &amp; Peacocks), that which other nations enjoyed ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, we enjoyed them altogether. Our honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne was ſpread, no feare to him that went out, or to him that came in, every one ſate under his own vine, &amp;c. Theſe advantages hadſt thou ô England above other people. Yet thy (Chiefly) lay in this; Thou didſt enjoy the oracles of God, diſpenſed by a ſound, boly, faithfull miniſtrie. By meanes whereof thy land was as the garden of ſpices, many thouſands of thy people are gone to heaven, and many thouſands yet alive have by their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie received and taſted ſo much of Chriſt's ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, for which they ſhall bleſſe God to all eternitie. What ayleth thee ô Land, that thy Miniſters are become hatred in the houſe of thy God, their names a ſcorne &amp; deriſion? What evill have they brought unto thee, that thou art weary of them? Nay, may not the Lord expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate the caſe with thee, and ſay wherein have I weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101164:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>thee, ô Land, teſtifie againſt me, I have not wearied thee with coſtly ſacrifice and incenſe? Why is that ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der maintenance become a burden unto thee now at laſt? Is not my Goſpell worth thy Tenths? Thou oweſt to thy Miniſter even thy ſelfe alſo, <hi>Philem. v.</hi> 19. and doſt thou begrudge them of thy Temporalls. O England, art thou become a land of <hi>Gadarens,</hi> that to ſave thy Tithes wilt ſend away thy Preachers? Is thy ſoule worth no more then the price of theſe periſhing things, Conſider what the change will be: haſt thou forgot thy bleſſed Sabaths, and the fruitfull ſolemnities of them, thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Communion with God in the Sacraments, in prayer and praiſe? Would it not be a ſad time to ſee a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, not of Bread, but of hearing the word of the Lord? To ſee the ſongs and ſolemnities of the Temple turned into howlings? <hi>To ſee thoſe holy and beautifull houſes, where our Fathers praiſed God, to be burnt with fire, and all our pleaſant things to be laid waſte? Eſa</hi> 64.11. (It was the Churche's complaint there) what is it an honour to thee, that thy Miniſters be of the baſeſt of thy people? To ſtarve them that feed thee; yea that ſpend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to feed thee? Will it not be griefe of heart to ſee the Candleſticke without a light? The Table without Bread? That there be neither Light nor Food in the houſe of God? God be mercifull to an unthankfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O our God, however it ſhall pleaſe thee to afflict us, doe not take thy Goſpell from us. Though thou doſt feed us with Bread and Water of Affliction: yet let not our Paſtors bee hid in a corner, but let our eyes ſee our Teachers, and our hearts heare the ſecret voice of the Spirit, accompanying it, This is the good way walk in it. And according to thy good promiſe be with thy holy ones, to the end of the world. Let the bleſſing of</hi> Levi <hi>reſt upon their heads,</hi> Deut. 33.8, 10, 11.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:101164:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101164:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>2.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>To the one a Savour of &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Savour of death unto death,</hi> (that is) a deadly ſavour, an occaſion of their farther hardning and impenitencie. The Goſpell is to them a dead unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourie thing, they gather poiſon out of the word of life. To the other ſort, a Savour of life, (that is) It is a quickning word, they feele ſome life in it: and this vitall Savour is unto life eternall. It follows,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>3</label> The ſame Miniſter, and the ſame doctrine preacht in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently to all, hath not the ſame effects in all. It wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in a far different manner. To the one it is ſavorie, and fruitfull unto life. To the other it is odious, irkſome and unſavorie, unfruitfull, and an occaſion of their far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hardning, it yeelds death unto them. Even as the ſame ſun doth harden the clay, and melt the wax. And as the ſame Star is to ſome a morning-Star bringing light and day, to others an evening-ſtar bringing darkneſſe &amp; night. So the Goſpell is a comfort to ſome, a terrour to others, bringing light and life to ſome, to others dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofs </seg>
               </label> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23, 24. <hi>We preach Chriſt crucified to the Jewes a ſtumbling-blocke, to the Greeks fooliſhnes. But unto them which are called both Jew and Greeke, Chriſt the power of God and wiſdome of God.</hi> The Jews ſeek after ſignes, they ſee Chriſt crucified through weakneſſe, therefore they ſtumble at him. The Greeks ſeek after wiſdome, &amp; arguments of reaſon, they diſcourſe of ſin and ſalvation, and the life to come, according to their wit, and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101164:9"/>Principles. Tis fooliſhneſſe to tell them of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by a condemned perſon, Againe, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>I lay in Sion a chiefe corner-ſtone.</hi> But there be different o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of him, and accordingly different manners of receiving him; to ſome <hi>he is pretious;</hi> nothing ſo pretious as Chriſt, nothing ſo honoured as Chriſt, nothing ſo deare: To the other, he is ſet aſide as a veſſell of no uſe, yea he is unto them <hi>a Rock of offence,</hi> they daſh againſt him, and periſh: the one believe on him, and are not confounded; to the other he is a rock of offence to their fall and ruine through their owne diſobedient hearts. And thus <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaid of Chriſt Luk. 2.34. That Chriſt is <hi>ſet for the riſing and falling of many in Iſrael:</hi> Some that ſtand in high eſteeme in the Church ſhall fall, others that be low, ſhall be raiſed &amp; comforted: one proofe more, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>Paul's</hi> hearers; <hi>ſome ſpeake againſt the things which were ſpoken by Paul. But as many, as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ordained to life believed;</hi> God who hath ordained the end, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; hath prepared the meanes, and makes the ſame effectuall to ſome, which are not to others. From this his place it's cleare: that when ſeverall perſons here the ſame Sermon, ſee the ſame miracles, enjoy the ſame word of life, yet to ſo it proves a ſavour of life &amp;c. 1. The one is <hi>effectus per ſe,</hi> the proper effect of the Goſpell; the other <hi>per accidens</hi> through the frowardneſſe of them that heare it. 2. Theſe places ſhew what Chriſt, and the word preached are (occaſionally) to ſome men through their voluntary reſiſting againſt God and his ordinances. And not what they are (intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally) in God's purpoſe and thoughts, when he firſt gave the Goſpell. He intended them for good, though men pervert them to their hurt. 2. Againe, it is a deadly ſavour, not as if the Goſpell of its owne nature breathed out death to any; for, it is <hi>the miniſtry of life.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7. and the <hi>Power of God to ſalvation;</hi> but by reaſon that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinners will not be healed, they ſet themſelves againſt it, and ſo it turnes to their condemnation.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101164:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Q. </seg>
               </label> Whats the Reaſon of this different manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: why life to ſome, and death to others, why not death to all?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
               </label> The Anſwer muſt be divided, (for, there is not one cauſe of both.) Of the event <hi>perſe,</hi> which is unto life, there is one cauſe) of the event <hi>per accidens,</hi> which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, there is another cauſe: The Reaſon of the event <hi>perſe,</hi> is God's grace, which opens the heart, and bows the will to embrace the word of life, ſo amongſt <hi>Pauls</hi> Hearers, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>As many as were ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, Believed:</hi> ordaining to eternall life went before their believing. So when the ſeaventie returned, and told our Saviour, what good ſucceſſe their preaching had abroad, whereas the <hi>Jews</hi> which heard Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, repented not, Chriſt breaketh out into an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's love, <hi>I thanke thee O Father of heaven and earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe;</hi> and what doe we learne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence. 'It does not goe by wit or learning; for, it was hid from the prudent and wiſe. Nor yet by the excellency of the Preacher; for, Chriſt was greater then the Diſciples, yet their Miniſtry was of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter efficacy.</p>
            <p>Where then lies the difference? God was pleaſed to reveale thoſe myſteries to Babes. <hi>Even ſo, becauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good in thy ſight. Mat.</hi> 11.25, 26. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20, 21: To know theſe myſteries is the <hi>Guift of God,</hi> and being a gift, it is free for him to give it to one, and not to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Remarkable to this purpoſe is that <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. <hi>But the Election hath obtained it.</hi> The queſtion is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, verſ. 1. <hi>Hath God caſt away his people?</hi> No, He proves it, firſt, in himſelfe, I am a Jew, therefore all are not caſt away. Secondly, God hath not caſt away his people, whom he foreknew. What then, how ſtands the matter? Why, this is the concluſion, the election hath obtained it, the reſt were blinded; the elect have a preeminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reſt, the God of grace doth ſhine into their hearts the light of the knowledge of the glory of God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101164:10"/>in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. But the God of the world hath blinded the minds of them that believe not, leaſt the light of the glorious goſpell of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Of the event <hi>per accidens,</hi> occaſionally, it provesa ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of death to ſome.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Now let us conſider what thoſe occaſions are? or what thoſe diſtempers are in the parties themſelves, ſeeing the difference cannot be in the ordinance it ſelfe, which is the ſame to both, it muſt be ſought elſewhere.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> 1 The Goſpell therefore proves a ſavour of death. Firſt, ſometimes on the Miniſters part, when they doe not deale faithfully, when by flatteries, they ſay to the ſoules that ſhall die, yee ſhall live: This the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14. <hi>They dealt falſely, they healed the hurt of the daughter of my people ſlightly, ſaying, Peace, peace, when there was no peace.</hi> Thus it comes to paſſe, that the poore ſoule is hardned, when men preach the free grace of God and mercy, without laying before people the conditions, whereupon mercy is promiſed; when we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them life, and doe not preſſe upon them the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of holy walking in the path of life, mercy without repentance. People muſt be ſound in repentance, in faith, in puritie of conſcience, elſe we can promiſe them no peace of conſcience; we muſt put a difference betweene pretious and vile <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.19. We muſt not preach as if all alike ſhould be ſaved, as if the outward ordinances and communion therein were ſufficient; unleſſe yee be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in the heart, as well as in the fleſh, baptized with the ſpirit, inwardly called, really converted, &amp;c. Ye cannot enter into the kingdome of heaven, we muſt deale clearely in this point, elſe we delude the people. Wee muſt tell you, that 'tis not all your moralities, nor all your civilities, nor all your formalities in prayer and comming to Church, that makes a ſound Chriſtian; yee muſt be humbled, &amp; brought into covenant with Chriſt; whatſoever is ſhort of regeneration, is ſhort of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101164:10"/>Thus <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. profeſſion of Chriſt's name will not ſerve the turne. A diſtinguiſhing Miniſtry is the ſavory ſaving Miniſtry, which lets you ſee in what ſtate you are, whether in nature, or in Grace; Sheepe, or Goates &amp;c. A promiſcuous preaching of Chriſt's mercy to all without any other diſtinguiſhing markes, doth cauſe a mis-application of the Goſpell; &amp; men, that are ſons of death, thinke themſelves Children of life. Poore ſouls are blinded to their deſtruction through Miniſters fault: we muſt not warrant repentance to be true without faith, nor faith to be true in any, that ſee not their curſed ſtate in nature, that feele not their need of faith by reaſon of ſin and miſery. Nor can we war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant faith in any Body, that is not become a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and the new-borne deſire to grow by the ſincere milke of the word &amp;c. The Goſpell preaching mercy to the Lumpe is a truth, But that word muſt be rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and mercy applyed to whom it is promiſed.</p>
            <p>On the peoples part, foure waies. 1. By reaſon of their careleſneſſe, cuſtomarineſſe in religion, not Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Trying, and Applying to themſelves in particular the markes and truths deliver'd: when the faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhew the world how their ſins are pardoned, and how they muſt get into the Covenant of Grace to have their deadly woe removed, people doe not marke it, nor take paines about it, but eſteeme of it as a light matter, as if God were beholding to them for hearing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Salvation. This Cuſtomarineſſe you diſcover by careleſneſſe in hearing, and after hearing; ſome lay them to ſleepe, others play with their Children, others place themſelves out of hearing &amp;c. people plainly ſhew, that they come not, as people, that are to deale in matters of ſalvation and damnation, <hi>If our Goſpell be hid, 'tis hid to them, that are loſt;</hi> the light thereof ſhines cleare, but the fault is in your ſelves, you are content to be blindfolded and holden back from ſo great a treaſure as is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Goſpell. O Is it not a ſad thing (and yet too
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101164:11"/>true) that in many houſes, not one of the familie knowes himſelfe to be ſaved? All ſuch ſaving knowledge is a myſterie to them? you think you have repented, becauſe you have ſorrowed for ſome particular ſin; and that you have faith, becauſe you hold ſome doctrines of faith, (the Divels doe the ſame.) But how to know your ſelves to be the elect of God, though it be clearly laid forth by your Miniſters, yet that heavenly truth is not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, becauſe you are not carefull to trie your ſelves, and to prove your eſtate to be good. All is but a dead and unſavorie thing upon your ſpirits. Whereas the conſcionable hearer doth finde ſpirituall life in ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing truths; he is comforted and quickned, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his name to be written in the book of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, it proves a deadly ſavour to you by reaſon of the diſcontent, pride, ſelfe-love, and contentiouſneſſe of your ſpirits, that will not endure to be reproved, or ſearched; you ſtumble at the word through diſobedience, be angry with that which ſhould doe you moſt good, quarrell at the Light. Now when people be thus ſettled on their Lees; when they have ſuch ſtumbling-blocks of iniquitie in their hearts, now I ſay, that word which brings life to others, brings death to you, you ſee no good in it. As if you ſtir a dunghill, it ſtinks the worſe, ſo if you rake in a fowle heart, the mud and filth that's in it doth ariſe, and corruption works the more; O what reaſonings and ſidings with ſin and Satan? ô what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and oppoſition againſt the Light? <hi>Sin taking occaſion by the Commandement,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paul, wrought in me all maner of concupiſcence, Rom.</hi> 7.8. The Law did put no evill moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into his heart; but <hi>wrought,</hi> (that is) <hi>did ſtir it up;</hi> it was there before, it ſet corruption aworke. If the word doe not prevaile to ſubdue and purge out corruption; then it ſtirs it up and ſets it a working, and ſo proves a ſavour of death to you. Whereas the ſame doctrines, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, and ſearching trialls to the ſaved ones do yeeld a ſavour of life. Good is the word of the Lord, I am vile,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101164:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>I am uncleane, thy word is truth: <hi>Hic ure, hic ſeca, ut in aeternum parcas.</hi> Let thy word cut and not ſpare my heart, my deareſt corruptions: Let it diſcover my ignorance, my hypocriſie, my unſoundneſſe in repentance, my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie in duties, &amp;c. It ſhall not be unto me as an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſword, but as a Surgion's knife, that cuts to heale my wound, my feſtered ſoule. Although the word puts you to ſtrong fightings, to ſad feares, to doubtings and diſputings within your ſelfe, yea to lowd cries through depth of ſorrow, and bring you into combates with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; yet you will ſee, there is a ſavour of life in it; you will not let goe your hold of it, till it bring forth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto victorie. As one in danger of drowning, will take hold of a naked ſword, though it cut him, rather then ſinke in the water; it is better to be cut then drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: ſo the ſaved ones will keep and hold faſt the word, though with ſome great difficulties, rather then give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their ſoule into the Divel's hands, and themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perdition. Thus the word is a ſavour of life to them, though it cut, and ſmart, there is life in it, it is good, it's ſweet, they relliſh ſpirituall counſell in it, it proves to them a true and faithfull word. Thus by occaſion of peoples frowardneſſe, and diſcontent at the word it proves <hi>odor mortis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, By reaſon of prejudices and hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the Preacher, many a ſound truth is loſt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relliſhed for the ſake of him, that brings it, as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid of <hi>Micaiah, Here is one Prophet of the Lord: but I hate him, &amp;c.</hi> If the ſame truths were delivered by other men, O how pretious would they be? But ſuch a man I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to heare, though they cannot be charged with negligence or unſufficiency, in their Miniſtry, nor with ſcandall and diſorder in their lives. But ſome by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpects turnes away our hearts from them, and from their Doctrine for their ſakes; As ſome are young, and have no judgement, ſome are old, and they wax childiſh againe: ſome are rich, and they are covetous, ſome are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101164:12"/>poore, and therefore Contemptible, and we will not be taught by ſuch: ſome tell the peoples faults in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and meddle with that they have nothing to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and we doe not like that; for, they are malitious, and at enmitie with us: ſome are not of our ſide, &amp;c. And though none of theſe things be faults, yet people ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at them. It therefore much availes, with what affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions we come to heare. The ignorant and ſcandalous, the ſuperſtitious and factious, are juſt offences, unfit to be Teachers. But doe not lay a ſtumbling-block in thine own way, becauſe the perſon is not in every reſpect ſuch a one as thou deſireſt. If thou wert on the Scaffold to be beheaded, thou wouldſt welcome a pardon, though brought by the hand of a perſon, not ſo well thought of: ſo &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, a ſavour of death, becauſe people doe not heare the words, as the word of God, but of man. People doe not come to it, nor look upon it as an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of divine authoritie, but an exerciſe of humane wit and charitie, and accordingly they doe not receive it with reverence and faith; but with the head, with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe or diſpraiſe, according as the matter is carried. See 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Yee received it not as the word of men, but as it is in truth the word of God;</hi> that's the right way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving heavenly truths, not becauſe we ſay it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is God's word; and that's the true way to profit by what we heare; for, then it worketh effectually in them that believe. An ordinary retainer to a Kings Court may tell what the Embaſſadours meſſage is, but that's of no reſpect, unleſſe the Embaſſadour doe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, as from his Maſter that ſent him: So, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I have ſeene it printed, and heard it ſpoken by way of complaint, that the ordinances now adaies have loſt their converting power. And well it may be ſo, when as gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted men are heard with equal reſpect to God's Miniſters. Gifted men are like but a retainer to the Court, they cannot preach in the name of the Lord; they cannot lay
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101164:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>obedience upon mens conſcience; and why? Becauſe the Lord hath not ſent them: the Lord ſpeaks not by them, they ſpeake of themſelves. And ſince they are cried up, and God's meſſengers decried, the conſcience of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is at libertie, to obey, or not obey the word. And doubtleſſe much is to be laid to their charge for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall contempt of the Goſpell preached: it's made a matter of indifferencie whom we heare &amp;c. Beware of that errour. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.29. <hi>For, he taught them, as one having autority.</hi> So muſt we preach, and ſo muſt you heare.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Signe. </seg>1</label> For Conviction, Becauſe ſome gather poyſon from the ſweeteſt flowers, &amp; from the moſt wholeſome truths, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Doctrine it ſelfe; ſuch is the blindneſſe of ſome, and the perverſneſſe of other mens wits &amp; reaſonings. As for Example, the Comfortable Doctrine of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation yeelds a deadly ſavour to ſome; for, thus they argue; If God have appointed, who ſhall be ſaved, and that none ſhall be ſaved but the elect, then (ſay ſome) To what end ſhould the Goſpell be preached to repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates? In vaine is all prayer, preaching, and holy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours? If we be not elected, All our ſtriving is in vaine; if we be elected, we ſhall be ſaved, though we doe take ſuch paines about ſalvation &amp;c. This Doctrine you ſee yeelds a deadly ſavour to ſome, it's made a cloack to careleſneſſe and ſecurity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> Firſt, conſider the nature of God's decree; it is not a ſimple abſolute, peremptory ordayning of an end with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meanes; God's Act electing is Relative and Copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive with reſpect unto Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. <hi>He choſe us in him, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love,</hi> with 2 Th. 2.13. <hi>We are bound to give thankes to God for you, brethren; Becauſe God hath from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning choſen you to ſalvation through ſanctification of the ſpirit, &amp; beliefe of the truth.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.21. <hi>If a man therefore purge himſelfe from theſe, he ſhall be a veſſell of honour &amp;c.</hi> Theſe things are conjoyned; God's elect are not a profane
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101164:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>berren, uncleane kind of people, good for nothing, but holy, pure, fruitfull, and by ſuch good workes is our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling made ſure, 2 Pet. 1.10. And the proper reſult of this Doctrine is this, I will ſtrive to be holy, to purify my conſcience from all iniquitie. They which make Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their buſineſſe &amp;c. have the ſeal of Election upon their hearts. Hence they thus reaſon; Is not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my election unto life, worth all the paines, that I ſhall take to attaine it? and worth all the ſweete ſins which I am to relinquiſh for it: will all the world be able to recompence the loſſe of my ſoule? of my God? what ſtronger motive to Godlineſſe, can be propoſed to an unconverted ſoule? Secondly, eſpecially conſidering that this Doctrine does not tell any man in particular, that he is a Reprobate; noe man can know it by himſelfe, becauſe thy preſent ſins are not above God's Grace; God is above thy naughty heart; and therefore we preach the Goſpell of ſalvation to men, as ſinners, (not as elect or reprobate) to all ſinners without exception; we bid them come to Chriſt, and he will heale them. We challen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge all the world to name one man or woman, that ever repented in vaine, and praied or ſought God in vaine. It is a dangerous temptation of the Devill, in ſtead of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpell, to be inquiſitive in the firſt place, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we be elected or not; obey, and thou art Elected. 1 Th: 1.4, 5, 6. <hi>Knowing, brethren beloved, your election of God: for, our Goſpell came not unto you in word onely, but in power and in the holy Ghoſt and in much aſſurance, as ye know what &amp;c.</hi> Therefore art thou a ſinner? then Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus, Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, the cheife of ſinners; Preach this Goſpell to every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that every creature may have a ground to believe and live; for, who ſoever commeth unto him, he will in noe wiſe caſt off. Reaſon thus, The Lord freely offereth mercy, if I will but forſake my ſins. He aſſures me, that if I ſeeke &amp; ſtrive I ſhall not ſeek in vaine; that he awaites, that he may be mercifull unto me; that where the meanes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101164:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>are uſed, the end will be obtained. Bleſſed arge they, that hungre &amp; thirſt after righteouſneſſe. Praying, Preaching, and ſeeking, are not in vaine; for, every one that ſeeketh, findeth <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.9.10, <hi>Aſke, and it ſhall be given unto you ſeeke, and yee ſhall find &amp;c.</hi> It was a good ſaying of <hi>Sarah Wight</hi> to a Gentlewoman in ſpirituall diſtreſſe, goe, ſay to God, heale me, I have ſinned, heale my backſlidings. Oh but I am no better for ſaying it, when I have no heart nor ſpirit to pray, yet (quoth <hi>Sarah Wight</hi>) Say it, though you be not better, becauſe God bids you ſay it, Say it, and ſay it againe, till he heale you: it may be he will come in, when you ſay it; if you can but ſay it with your lips, the everlaſting Armes of God can reach you, when you cannot reach him; wee muſt looke at God's revealed will, that we ſhould pray and waite on him in his waies. <hi>Peter</hi> bid <hi>Simon Magus</hi> Pray. In preaching the Goſpell, light, motion, and power goes out to all, which they that reſiſt, periſh, not becauſe they could not beleive, but becauſe they reſiſt and refuſe to obey. What greater encouragement to holineſſe and to duty, to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of piety, and Chriſtian endeavours after Grace? This they do ſavour, that are ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance. </seg>2</label> The doctrine of free grace &amp; redemption is a ſavour of death to ſome, it hardens them to ſecuritie. Thus ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer upon it, Chriſt hath done all, we muſt not thinke to be ſaved by duties, or by ordinances, by humbling our ſelves, &amp;c. that's legall. Therefore others ſay, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell offers mercy to all ſinners, at all times. What of that? Therefore there's time enough to come in, and be ſaved. This is a deadly inference too; an inference of death to thee. But the ſaved ones gather life of it, O here's comfort for me, I may freely come to God, accept of peace and be one with him; I will not caſt away his mercie, I will not put a ſcorne upon his offer of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation Chriſt hath done all, that a Chriſt or a Mediatour ought to doe, both for purchaſing and applying ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to me; I muſt now doe what a ſinner's part is, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101164:14"/>to accept of it, to humble himſelfe, and pray &amp; obey him, and live to him, that gave himſelfe for me. Chriſts part is to give &amp; beſtow the graces of faith, repentance, and humiliation. But it is the ſinner's part to exerciſe them. Free-grace does not ſet the heart at libertie to luſts.</p>
            <p>In the doctrine of free-grace &amp; redemption by Chriſt God hath this purpoſe, and aime (namely) to ſhew a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ground, upon which all humbled ſinners might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of peace. And likewiſe that there might be a viſible rule of rejecting all, that wilfully contemne their owne peace.</p>
            <p>The doctrine of free will: The Goſpell teacheth that we are dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, unable to raiſe our ſelves to ſpirituall life. And that it is the ſpirituall grace of God, by which we are converted and raiſed. This yeelds to ſome a deadly inference, therefore in vaine is the uſe of meanes urged, and people leave all to God in a brutiſh way, ſaying <hi>as it pleaſeth God, it is God that muſt doe it for us, we have no power of our ſelves &amp;c.</hi> This is a deadly inference, it ſlaies many a ſoule. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in other affaires, we reaſon quite contrary; I am ſicke and cannot help my ſelfe, therefore I will goe to the Phyſitian; cannot read nor write, therefore I will goe to ſchoole to be taught. I cannot tell how to make a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tto till the ground, &amp;c. Therefore what ſhall I ſay? I muſt refer all to God; nay, but therefore I will get the skill &amp;c. The ſaved ones will make other concluſions from ſuch doctrines; becauſe we have no ſtrength, no help on earth, therefore I will to my prayers, to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to get help from heaven. Thus it is with Gods ordinances and the pretious truths thereofas with phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, it is given for the Patients good, but many times through the diſtemper of his body, it doth him hurt. Thus wholſome doctrine through mens perverſe reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings doth turne to their deſtruction, through thoſe falſe hardning inferences, is a ſavour of death. Beware
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101164:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>leaſt the Lord be once provoked to give up obſtinate ones to their own hearts luſts; permitting them to daſh againſt Chriſt and other meanes of eternall life, and ſo through his juſt judgement they be blinded to their end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſerie and miſchiefe: as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81.11, 12. <hi>But my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would not hearken to my voice, and Iſrael would none of me; ſo I gave them up to their owne hearts luſts, and they walked in their own counſelles.</hi> So <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.39. <hi>For judgement I am come into the world, that they which ſee, might be made blinde:</hi> wretched ſinners who acknowledge their owne ignorance, they ſhall ſee: But they which think they are wiſe, too wiſe to be taught, they ſhall be delivered up to the blindneſſe of their own hearts. Which made an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſay, They that have deſpiſed God's inviting will, ſhall feele his revenging will.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Goe home, conſider, how 'tis with you,if the Mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrie have proved a ſavour of life to any of you, praiſe his mercy for it, it proceeded from the father of lights; But if a dead thing, and unſavorie upon your ſpirits, blame your ſelves, ſearch and you ſhall finde, that ſome of the forementioned diſtempers have been the occaſion theerof. Goe over the particulars; Through your own fault it is, that the word of life yeelds no lively ſavour to your ſoules, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Signe. </seg>2</label> For conviction and humiliation; Look to it, the word worketh one way or other, if not to life, it will be unto death; it is ſharper then a two-edged ſword, which cuts on both ſides, for the hardning or converting of the ſinner: if a man believe and obey it, it is life to him, it brings about his good and ſafetie; if not, it falleth a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king alſo to augment his naturall blindneſſe &amp; hardneſſe, and to binde him guiltie unto judgement; it alwaies hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, or hurteth the hearer. Therefore you ſhall do well to obſerve what ſort of working it hath upon you, that ſo you may be framed to the better by it. Obſerve under which effect of it you lie; is it a ſavour of life or of death to you?</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101164:15"/>
            <p>For your Humiliation, and to break the heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, I will give foure Convictions, whereby it may appeare to your owne conſcience, that it is a dead, unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorie, unfruitfull thing unto you, that you never yet did relliſh any thing of life in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt is, Becauſe you take ſo little delight in it, and ſo little paines about it: for, 'tis the propertie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very bleſſed man to delight in the law of God, to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in it, to walk in it both day and night, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1.1, 2. My delight and my counſellonrs, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.24. How doth his ſoule break out in holy longings and love to the law of God? And alſo to take paines for this bread of life; the Queene of the South came from the uttermoſt parts of the earth to heare the wiſdome of <hi>Solomon, Mat:</hi> 12.42. <hi>Whereſoever the carkaſſe is, thither will the Eagles be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together.</hi> As Eagles by a naturall inſtinct flie to their food: ſo where Chriſt is preached, believers by the motion of the ſpirit, will reſort to him. Can yee taſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and no ſweetneſſe in it? Can yee want bread, &amp; take no paines for it? <hi>Take us and all we have for Bread,</hi> ſaid they to <hi>Joſeph:</hi> you labour for meat, that periſheth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there's life in it: ſo would you after the meat, that endureth to eternall life, if yee did relliſh it. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour not for meat which periſheth, but for that meat which endureth unto everlaſting life,</hi> (that is) labour more for eternall life: O what a deale of contriving, &amp; ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of unwearied diligence to raiſe an eſtate? to raiſe poſteritie, to enlarge poſſeſſions? to live? And yet how it ſhall goe with you, and how you ſhall live eternally, did did never put you to the trouble of one houre's ſerious conſideration or paines: God is our chiefe good, and all our happineſſe conſiſts in his love, &amp; therefore it ſhould be valued and ſought above all things; The very buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we have in this world is to glorifie God, and to provide for a better life. And yet how little doe you ſet by the meanes of life? You will not be at the paines to acquaint your ſelves or familie with the doctrine of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101164:15"/>I cannot perſwade you to read the Bible, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good books, or to learne the grounds of Religion in ſome Catechiſme. or to ſanctiſie the Lord's day in holy exerciſes of prayer, ſelfe-examination, Hearing the word.</p>
            <p>(Nay, with much coldneſſe do you come to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation). Theſe things are burdenſome, irkſome, unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorie to you, you finde no life in this holy courſe; and why? Becauſe you are dead ſoules. Let me ſpeake unto you Husbandmen, Tradeſmen, and Labourers, conſider your waies, and your daies ſpent in toyle and labour, up to worke early, there's much to be done, in the mornings no time, in the evenings the head is heavie, unfit for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall matters. The Sabbath is your day, God in mercy provided it for your reſt, for your ſoules refreſhing alſo; yet that day is too much from your worldly buſineſſe: In the morning, goe ſee ſuch a piece of ground, or ſuch a parcell of ſheep, or ſuch a cuſtomer, &amp; then to Church if time be left: poore ſoules, what doe you thinke? Is this to delight in the word? O how little doe you ſet by heaven? If you did but take halfe ſo much paines and delight for heaven, as for the world, I ſhould think, you did finde ſome ſpirituall life in the word.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake to you, Careles daughters, perhaps once in the day you give us the hearing: and ſtay at home the other part; you trifle away the Sabbath-mornings about Children: you ſpend idly as much time, as your neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry affaires of houſe require, therefore yee cannot come to Church; perhaps in the afternoone, yee have ſome Cloaths to mend, or ſtarch: This providing for, and trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the body is your Sabbath-daie's worke, as if you were borne to be drudges and poore, and ſo to the grave. O what a fearefull ſpirit of ſlumber is upon our people? (Not more ignorant, earthly-minded in any pariſh) there is no ſigne that you relliſh the Miniſtrie of the word, as a word of life, you taſte no ſuch thing in it, all your carriage ſavours of death; if you had taſted life in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101164:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>it, you would have love to it, and thinke nothing too much, that you could poſſibly doe. You would have zeale to rouze you, and faith, like the ſpring in a watch to ſet all the wheeles of your ſoules agoing. The zeale of thy houſe hath even eaten me up.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſion. </seg>
               </label> I conclude with that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16. <hi>Looke diligently, leaſt there be any Fornicator, or prophane perſon, as</hi> Eſau: <hi>who for one morſell of meat ſold his Brith-right:</hi> He relliſhed good in the morſell of meat, none in his Birth-right. <hi>Eſau</hi> muſt have food; what? with the loſſe of his Birth-right? The Conſtant call of the Scripture is, Strive to enter in at the ſtraight gate. Work out your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with feare and trembling. Walk preciſely not as fooles, but as wiſe. Conforme your ſelves not to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world. The judgement of the carnall world is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; Theſe rules are too ſtrict, and preciſe, if we live by them, we were as good goe out of the world. O are yee wiſer then all the world? Shall I make myſelfe a laughing-ſtock to the world? Nay, but will you be wiſer then God?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2, 16.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe third Conviction followes, whereby it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to your conſciences, that hetherto the Goſpell hath been but a dead and unſavorie thing upon your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and that is by the little account of any ſpirituall good received by all that you heare; it hath left dead hearts, dead, unrenued affections, under an outſide pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; you have not felt the experience of the things taught and heard, you doe not underſtand it feelingly; it affects not, it alters not the judgement, nor affections.</p>
            <p>There is a twofold knowledge of matters in Religion the one is by rule, the other is by proofe, triall, or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; the one is gotten out of the letter of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only, &amp; ſo men have it but by rule; the other is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſcripture too: but it is felt to be the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101164:16"/>ſword of the ſpirit for the bettering of us. As in all trades and ſciences, there is a knowledge, which one get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth by rule and inſtruction only, yet for want of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when, where, &amp; how to buy, ſell, plant, &amp;c. he may decay and grow behind hand: So the Chriſtian hath not only the rule, but the proofe of his knowledge, how it hath been effectuall to aſſure him of his own ſalvation, to change his heart, to comfort, to overcome temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how good God is in his waies, &amp;c. He is the true Chriſtian indeed, (to the one it's a dead, to the other a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſavour). As for example, He that only reads in a booke, that he is miſerable by nature, and what his ſoule ſtands in need of, but never felt himſelfe miſerable, nor felt his ſeverall wants, is dead, while he liveth. He that reads in a book, or heares in a Sermon, what repentance is, what the cleanſing of the heart is, what ſtriving of the ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fleſh is, &amp;c. But never felt his owne heart purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his owne conſcience ſtricken with feares, &amp;c. This man hath a rule, but not the ſavour of life in the Goſpell. To read or heare of comforts is one thing, to feele them in the conſcience is another. 'Tis one thing to be of ſuch a judgement in matters of religion, to hold ſuch and ſuch principles, to be right in his tenets, and to hold that men muſt be religious. 'Tis another thing to be ſo, to feel our unkindneſſe to Chriſt, our deadneſſe of heart to him, our pantings and longings after Chriſt. A man by the light of Scripture may confeſſe, that God is the beſt por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he, that enjoyes God, hath all, that all earthly, things are periſhing contentments; yet will not for Gods ſake, for conſcience ſake, forſakeany thing. This man's judgement ſaies, that God is our chiefe God, but his heart and affections never ſaid ſo. But he that can take up a Croſſe to follow Chriſt, deny himſelfe, cut off a right hand for righteouſneſſe ſake, he ſaies indeed, and in heart, God is my portion, God is my chiefe good. <hi>The ſavour of Chriſt's knowledge</hi> doth import a ſenſitive expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall feeling knowledge: ſuch as we have of fire,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101164:17"/>that it is hot, of honie, that it is ſweet, &amp;c. Taſte ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conviction. </seg>4</label> Look what it is, that does moſt affect thee in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. What matter? what manner of preaching? There is much to be diſcerned by mens praiſes or diſpraiſes, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or diſliking in this kinde. Imagine a carnall and ſpirituall hearer conferring about a Sermon: was it a good Sermon? Yes. What was the doctrine? What was the reaſon, what have you learnt by it? My memory is ſhort. A good ſermon, and you get no good by it? What did moſt affect you, O'twas a deep ſermon. He did handle the Antinomians notably, or he did worthily confute the errours of the times. What elſe did you like? <hi>His manner of deliverie,</hi> it was delivered in good language, &amp; a good ſtile, and I like it well to have good matter cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in a good dreſſe. Yea but what was there of Chriſt in it? that might cleanſe the heart, bring one into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, crucifie your luſts, build you up in holineſſe, make you ſound in repentance? Yes, it was a morall good ſermon.) O but ſaid the ſpirituall man, may not you heare ſuch preaching all daies of your life, and yet be never the wiſer for your ſalvation? If you ſavour that which is but the naturall frothy part, that which is leaſt worthy of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in that work, are yee not carnall? if you commend and love that which you leaſt underſtand, and be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed beſt with that which doth tickle the eare, and not rectifie the conſcience, are yee not carnall? your carnall judgement in this point bewraies, that the Miniſtrie is not a Miniſtrie of life and power to thee, but of forme and moralitie, of good order; that it has not carried you beyond placing your religion in Baptiſme, in Church Conſtitutions, in outward garbs, and the ſmaller matters or bark of religion; your ſoules all the while being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the eſſentialls of Religion in power, &amp; puritie, in joy, in righteouſneſſe, in peace, in aſſurance of ſalvation. Whereas <hi>for the matter,</hi> that ſermon is beſt, wherein <hi>we manifeſt the truth, and commend our ſelves to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101164:17"/>the conſciences of men in the ſight of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. And for <hi>the manner,</hi> that is beſt which is ſet forth <hi>not in the enticing words of man's wiſdome, but in demonſtration of the ſpirit and power,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.3. It is a curſe to have the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <hi>in a ſtrange tongue,</hi> and ſo in a ſtile &amp; frame of words not eaſily underſtood by the people. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 9. <hi>Except yee utter words eaſie to be underſtood, how ſhall it be knowne, what is ſpoken? For, yee ſhall ſpeake into the ayre.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth reprove their carnall judgement in this point, becauſe they ſo much admired the gift of tongues <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21. Its a childiſh thing to be delighted with words, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. It is a judgement, to have the Goſpell in a way not underſtood; it is a ſigne God is not pleaſed to make the ſame a meanes of converſion. And therefore, foraſmuch as God doth make uſe of languages and tongues for a puniſhment; it is not fit matter of boaſting or glorying.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Carnall judgement; Come we to their diſpraiſes; How doe you like the ſermon? I doe not like it, 'twas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ordinary matter, yea ſcarce fit for a Sermon; he reproves ſuch petty faults, as ſleeping and playing with children, and dreſſing our ſelves, &amp;c. There's nothing of ſtudy of learning in it. He may preach after that rate all day long, &amp;c. 'Tis dead and unſavorie matter. Well, view it againe, ſuch matter was delivered, upon what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion? Why his doctrine from the Text was, that many heare the word to their hardning; and what think you, is it not true? Yes, goe on, what kinde of hearers were they that did ſo? Why they were the ſloathfull, careleſſe, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary hearers, that doe not examine and apply the Truths taught, or elſe heare it as an exerciſe of wit, or elſe be offended at the reproofes, &amp;c. And what think you of it? Is not all this true? Did he not prove it? Yes; there is ſpirituall matter in it, much morall evill and danger diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, not ſo much in the action, as in the heart; <hi>Res parva, magnum indicium;</hi> others ſee ſpirit and life in that matter, an evill heart of unbeliefe to lie at the bottome,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101164:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>if you doe compare the doctrine with the reproofes, and your ſoules with both, you will be found to be in a wrong courſe, you will be guided into a ſaving way, to walke in all well pleaſing before God. In their counſell, you will finde mercy and peace, their paths are <hi>paths of peace</hi> to deliver you from death</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You cannot ſlight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>nor deride religion, and yet at the ſame time live under the ſaving operation of the word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth doctrine followes, <hi>to the one-to the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to which of theſe is it a ſavour of life, &amp; to which of death. In them that are <hi>ſaved</hi> we are a <hi>ſweet ſavour of God unto life;</hi> in them, that <hi>periſh, a ſavour of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>4</label> Men are to be reckned in a ſtate of being ſaved, or of periſhing, according as they doe, or doe not receive the Miniſtry of the Goſpell, according as it is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorie and fruitfull, and good unto them, or a dead and unſavorie thing upon their ſpirits, (ſo are the perſons here diſtributed) God is glorified, and our Miniſtry accepted, both when people periſh, and when they are converted.</p>
            <p>Unto the ſaved ones, we are a ſavour of life, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſavour of death, and an occaſion of their hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Joh,</hi> 8.46.47. <hi>If I ſay the truth, why doe you not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveme? He that is of God, heareth Gods words; yee therefore heare them not, becauſe yee are not of God.</hi> Here our Saviour diſtinguiſheth them that be of God, from them that be not, by their different reſpect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of God's word; they that are of God, and led by his ſpirit will hearken &amp; endeavour to doe his will, the reſt who are not of God, but of Satan, hate and reſiſt the truth. So doth Chriſt mark out his own ſheep, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.27. <hi>My ſheep heare my voice and follow me, and I know them, and give unto them eternall life.</hi> So <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24, 26. He compares his hearers to wiſe and fooliſh builders of their owne ſalvation; the one who heareth and doth them is bleſſed, is ſafe from danger. Bleſſed are they, that heare the word and keep it. When people relliſh life in it, they are in the rank of bleſſed and ſaved ones;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101164:18"/>when they remaine dead under it, hardned in their ſins, it is a ſad fore-runner of their everlaſting deſtruction. How can this be ſo ſure an evidence of life and death ſeeing Hypocrites goe far, yea doe all in this kinde that a ſound Chriſtian may doe?</p>
            <p>They may doe much, as <hi>Herod</hi> did to <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel's</hi> hearers, cap. 33. 31. But herein they fall ſhort, they doe not yeeld the word a ſincere univerſall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect &amp; obedience; they heare, but doe it not; they heare, &amp; are offended at the word. It is the honeſt heart, that heares &amp; brings forth fruit with patience; an hypocrite, may do much, but he cannot do this; he may make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prayers, heare many ſermons, uſe faſting, cleave to the beſt ſide, approve of a ſound miniſtrie, forſake ſcandalous ſins, and be reformed in ſome meaſure by the word, &amp;c. Yet this he cannot doe, he cannot with an honeſt heart bring forth fruit with patience; he doth not in all things give the word a divine power over his heart; he cannot yeeld univerſall obedience thereto out of love to God; Therefore ſlight not this doctrine, the power of it expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your conſciences will witneſſe your ſoundneſſe, &amp; true fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt againſt all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>(<hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.161.) <hi>My heart ſtands in awe of God's word:</hi> you dare not reſiſt any truth, that yee heare, but you will yeeld unto it, make conſcience of it, deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to obey it, and put it in practiſe. This I ſay will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with you and for you, 1. <hi>Th.</hi> 1.5. For, the Goſpell came not unto you in word only, but alſo in power.</p>
            <p>Of Exhortation; Therefore come to the Miniſtrie; as to an ordinance wherein life and death are ſealed. Take theſe Motives. You muſt live for ever in heaven, or in hell: and the queſtion muſt be reſolved upon our obeying, or not obeying the Goſpell. Therefore bethinke thy ſelfe, what thou wert beſt to doe? Is not heaven worth all the ſins, which the word would crucifie in thee? And will thy unſubdu'd luſts, and the pleaſure thereof make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101164:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>for all the torments, which the diſobedient are ſure to endure in hell? Is thy conſcience convinced of this truth? If it be, how dareſt thou now goe on in thy common careleſſe courſe againſt the light of the word in thy own conſcience? How dareſt thou live as looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? heare as careleſly? Spend the Sabbath as profanely? ſlubber over the worſhip and ſervice of God as ſlightly, as formerly thou haſt done? To have this queſtion reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on thy ſide, me thinkes thy heart ſhould breake through all oppoſitions, ſcornes and temptations, and forthwith ſet thy ſelfe wholly about the worke, and to caſt off every weight, and with full reſolution of heart to lay thy ſoule at the feet of Chriſt, and his Miniſtrie, and ſay, Lord, here I am, what wilt thou have me to doe? Doe with my heart, and mould it to thine owne minde will.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>2</label> Conſider the terrour of the Lord againſt all wilfull people, that deſpiſe the ſavour of life: depart from mee yee workers of iniquitie into the place of torments; you know, the Sodomites are in an ill caſe in hell; yet it ſhall be more tolerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> then for thee, they ſinned againſt the light of nature, thou againſt the light of the Goſpell; they againſt the Law, thou againſt the Remedie, againſt the mercy of a Redeemer, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Of how much ſerer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath troden under foot the blood of the covenant &amp;c.</hi> Woe to poore ſinners for their madneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own ſoules. Conſider your caſe; art thou able to beare the wrath of God for ever? When he ſhall come in flames of fire, taking vengeance on them that know him not, and obey not the Goſpell of his Son. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. Thou canſt not endure the voice of the Cock, of a poore Miniſter, that awakens thy conſcience; How then wilt thou endure the voice of the Trumpet, <hi>Ariſe yee dead, and come to judgement?</hi> Death is terrible, &amp; ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is painfull; thou canſt not endure thy finger in the fire one houre, how then wilt thou endure everlaſting
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101164:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>fire. The tooth-ake, the ſtone, the Gout make thee roar, and cry out, O Lord help me: the torments of hell made <hi>Dives</hi> cry out, Send <hi>Lazarus</hi> to dip the tip of his finger in water to coole my tongue: you that will cry out then pity, pity a poore tormented ſoul, ſhould doe well to pity your ſelves now, when we cry out unto you to pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty your own ſoules; if thou wilt be entreated to pity thy ſelfe, thouwilt need no man's pity then; but here's your miſery, &amp; our infelicitie, you will not believe your own miſerie, you will not believe our report, if you did believe it, you would ſoone caſt away every ſin that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth on ſo faſt, you would no longer ſtand off, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver up your ſoules into Chriſt's doctrine to be transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, renued, and moulded by it; you would preſently enter into a ſtrict covenant with God to be his people, you would never content your ſelves with a cold, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, liveleſſe profeſſion, but labour for the life of grace, and that too, while the day of grace doth laſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive. </seg>3</label> It will torment you one day, to remember, what yee have loſt, what bleſſed opportunities, which cannot be recalled; to remember how eagerly the world was purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when your ſalvation lay at ſtake, &amp; if you had ſpent but one of thoſe yeares to get the knowledge of Chriſt unto unfeined converſion, you had been for ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, whereas now your miſerie is paſt recoverie, and all through your owne fault and doings. It will cut you to remember, how often did the Miniſter call upon me; how faine would he have had me to be ſaved, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and eſcape theſe torments, but I would not: I counted him mine enimie, I made a jeſt of his compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate beſeechings; when he told me 'twas not well with me, and ſhewed me my own heart; I thought him too buſie with other mens eſtates; though he were more willing to ſave me, then I my ſelfe to be ſaved: How freſh will theſe things come into thy minde &amp; gnaw thy heart, like a worme; thou wilt be a terrour to thy ſelfe. What will yee doe now upon theſe Motives? reſolve for life, before God take you away in his wrath.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
